<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pfps17-journal on Daniel Chen</title>
    <link>/tags/pfps17-journal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in pfps17-journal on Daniel Chen</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Daniel Chen {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/pfps17-journal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>NYC R Conference</title>
      <link>/2017/04/24/nyc-r-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/24/nyc-r-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just got back from the 3rd annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rstats.nyc/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NYC R Conference&lt;/a&gt; this past weekend.
I have been honored to be one of the few speakers for the 3rd year in a row.
This year&amp;rsquo;s talk, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chendaniely/rstatsnyc_2017-data_scientist&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;So You Want to be a Data Scientist&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
gave a whirlwind tour of the tools and skills needed to be a Data Scientist.
I conveyed all this information in 56 slides and did it in 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day before the conference,
I also ended up &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chendaniely/2017-04-20-nyp_value_institute&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;presenting&lt;/a&gt; my current work on behavior diffusion in social netowrks
and a little of my other work to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nyp.org/valueinstitute/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital’s Value Institute&lt;/a&gt;.
This was probably the more nerve wracking things I&amp;rsquo;ve had to do recently,
presenting my research to a few extremely talented and smart PhDs doing
health analytics for New York Presbyterian Hospital.
But, we had a lot of good meaningful discussion during the talk,
that went overtime and we were kicked out of the room.
That has to be a good sign, right?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working While Pursuing a PhD</title>
      <link>/2017/04/17/working-while-pursuing-a-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/17/working-while-pursuing-a-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My lab has extended me an opportunity to be a research scientist and helping out our current senior data scientist
with the daily analytics and IT support the lab needs.
It&amp;rsquo;s a very enticing opportunity, but I need to stop and think about my options&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d get paid more!
What kind of graduate student would not want that?
But I would really need to consider and clarify with my advisor and rest of my lab how
this can fit in with my PhD.
I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be doing my PhD longer than I have to,
and ideally I would be put on a series of projects that can be used for my final dissertation topic.
However, if I am a staff member of the lab, I will have less freedom of what my topic would be.
Of course, if I spent the after hours working on my dissertation,
I could do whatever I wanted, but that might not be a feasible solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job will give me financial stability,
but currently as a PhD student,
I have a lot of academic freedom that I might loose.
Since most of my work is computational,
it can easily be done remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily my advisor will becoming to down in a few weeks.
We&amp;rsquo;ll discuss this further then.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Education in the United States</title>
      <link>/2017/04/10/education-in-the-united-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/10/education-in-the-united-states/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As people start sharing their educational experiences from around the world,
I realized how lucky I am to have been educated in New York City,
and how much less the United States focuses on education when compared to many other countries around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The People that Keep Me Sane</title>
      <link>/2017/04/03/the-people-that-keep-me-sane/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/03/the-people-that-keep-me-sane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Coming from CUNY Hunter College, I never really had the typical &amp;lsquo;college experience&amp;rsquo;.
Going to college for me was almost no different than going to high school since so many people
were commuters; there was no campus, especially when compared to Virginia Tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I snowboard.
After not going during the 2 years of my master&amp;rsquo;s,
I decided the first thing I did when I started Tech was to find the ski/snowboarding club
and go on a big winter trip.
So I joined VT Snow my first year at VT,
and I got go fly out to Colorado for the first time ever to go Snowboarding.
I was the only graduate student who was in the club, and it was great.
I met a bunch of new friends who all knew how to snowboard and have fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also SCUBA dive.
My second year, I ended up getting involved with the SCUBA club (SCVT) because my family had a winter break trip
planned out to Australia.
I ended up getting my SDI Advanced Adventure Diver last semester to prepare for the trip to see the Great Barrier Reefs.
This semester I&amp;rsquo;m planning to finish my Rescue Diver,
and hope to start a Dive Master course over the summer.
Maybe by the time I finish my PhD I&amp;rsquo;ll also be a SCUBA instructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to have friends outside of your discipline, especially in a PhD program.
As isolating as life can be,
you definitely do not want to be constantly reminded about the work you know you should be doing when you&amp;rsquo;re
giving yourself a well needed mental break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that these sports require so much mental focus, allows me to just forget about everything else.
Plus the views on top of a mountain really makes you feel like you&amp;rsquo;re on top of the world,
and the calm weightless feeling while diving is meditative.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should You Attend Grad School?</title>
      <link>/2017/03/27/should-you-attend-grad-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/27/should-you-attend-grad-school/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been asked a few times about whether one should attend graduate school.
I usually follow up by asking whether they are planning to do a Master&amp;rsquo;s or a Doctorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it&amp;rsquo;s a master&amp;rsquo;s, sure, why not.
Master&amp;rsquo;s programs are typically no longer than 2 years and very well structured.
You come in with a cohort of students, and everyone struggles together and becomes friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PhD programs are much more variable and different.
First, the cohort of students are much smaller.
Second, unless there is Master&amp;rsquo;s along the way,
PhD programs will be unique to each student.
Meaning you&amp;rsquo;ll struggle on your own.
It&amp;rsquo;s important to consider your current support network when thinking about PhD programs.
I cannot stress this enough.
It&amp;rsquo;s a stressful, lonely, and isolating world out there,
and you really need to make sure you have a solid support network to help you though the ups and downs.
There is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://qz.com/547641/theres-an-awful-cost-to-getting-a-phd-that-no-one-talks-about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;awful cost&lt;/a&gt; to getting a PhD,
and there&amp;rsquo;s a reason why &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/careers/2017/04/phd-students-face-significant-mental-health-challenges&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mental health&lt;/a&gt; disorders are common among PhD students&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From NYC to Blacksburg, VA</title>
      <link>/2017/03/20/from-nyc-to-blacksburg-va/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/20/from-nyc-to-blacksburg-va/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m from New York City.
Born and raised in Queens, and went to school in Manhattan for high school, college, and masters.
So, coming down to rural Blacksburg, VA has been a big change in scenery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blacksburg is a beautiful town.
There are many aspects of the area that I love: clean air, quiet, and plenty of outdoor activities.
As someone pursuing a PhD, I am essentially a professional student,
so the lack of distractions is much appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do love the fact that many outdoor activities are so easily accessible in the area.
Hiking trails are as close as a 15 minute drive away,
The New River and Blacksburg Quarry for SCUBA diving are within 15 minutes away as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest things I miss about NYC is the food and pizza.
There is so much good ethnic cuisine that Blacksburg does not have.
The way around it is to try and cook it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had subscribed to Blue Apron last semester,
and it really kickstarted cooking meals at home versus buying and ordering food.
The 30-60 minutes to cook and eat is a nice distraction from the daily stress from school.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What You Call Yourself is Important</title>
      <link>/2017/03/13/what-you-call-yourself-is-important/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/13/what-you-call-yourself-is-important/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a PhD &lt;em&gt;Student&lt;/em&gt;, not a candidate&amp;hellip; yet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Learning Works</title>
      <link>/2017/03/06/how-learning-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/06/how-learning-works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Susan Ambrose&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/How-Learning-Works-Research-Based-Principles/dp/0470484101&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How Learning Works&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; is probably one of the best investments for people who teach.
The next best (time) investment is reading Greg Wilson&amp;rsquo;s paper on &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000research.com/articles/3-62/v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Software Carpentry: lessons learned&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve watched Greg Wilson&amp;rsquo;s corresponding &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FtKO619O5g0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PyCon 2014&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1e26rp6qPbA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SciPy 2014&lt;/a&gt; talk numerous times,
and is well worth the listen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching and Mentoring</title>
      <link>/2017/02/27/teaching-and-mentoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/27/teaching-and-mentoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Software-Carpentry&lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; has made be a better teacher because of the way we collect feedback during our workshops.
When teaching a technical class,
we use low-tech sticky notes to signify whether individuals need help or not:
Green for no help needed, Red for help needed.
This is extremely effective while teaching.
As an instructor all you need to look for is a red sticky note and you know someone has a question,
or if everyone has a green sticky note, the class is following along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The python community is proactive in mentoring.
During the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pydata.org/carolinas2016/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PyData Carolinas 2016&lt;/a&gt; conference,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WillingCarol&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Carol Willing&lt;/a&gt; talked about how small nudges and discussions can be enough to mentor someone.
I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to be a mentor to my students I teach though my lab&amp;rsquo;s summer program.
There is a misconception that mentoring is a &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; job.
It&amp;rsquo;s not.
The right piece of advice at the right time,
can change an individual&amp;rsquo;s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think about the most influential people in my life,
and it&amp;rsquo;s mainly a series of seemingly random encounters and discussions
that helped shaped the person I am today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where Do I Fit in Academia?</title>
      <link>/2017/02/20/where-do-i-fit-in-academia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/20/where-do-i-fit-in-academia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s always a good idea to take a break and think about all that&amp;rsquo;s going on in life in perspective.
As I approach the end of the coursework phase of my PhD program,
I need to think about what&amp;rsquo;s next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My preliminary exam&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but beyond that,
I need to think about the (glorious) life after I graduate.
Do I go to industry? or stay in Academia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, my duties are closer aligned to that of a scientific research software engineer.
I enjoy building scientific software and tools,
and enjoy doing data analysis.
What I dread is writing.
Mainly because I am slow and terrible at it.
While this is a feedback loop that I need to break,
my disdain for writing means that I am not academically &amp;ldquo;productive&amp;rdquo;.
No grants, no papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past year at Virginia Tech and taking the Future Professoriate Class,
working in the library seems like a good academic fit for my academic toolkit,
or my love for teaching has directed me into looking into Professor of Practice positions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Communicating Science</title>
      <link>/2017/02/13/communicating-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/13/communicating-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The communication science workshop at class reminds me of the various acting warm-up exercise I did when I took an acting class in high school.
The drills require individuals to coordinate and communicate with other people in the room,
but also serves as an icebreaker by doing &amp;lsquo;silly&amp;rsquo; things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first exercise we did in class was to describe our current research.
This is a skill that I have refined over the past few years as a PhD student.
I remember when I first started my PhD program,
I would try to describe my department, program, and current work &amp;lsquo;correctly&amp;rsquo;,
only to see a blank stare from the person I would be talking to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Genetics, Bioinformatics, and Computational Biology&amp;rdquo; is a lot of big words.
Furthermore, &amp;ldquo;Interdisciplinary between Mathematics, Statistics, Life Science, and Computer Science&amp;rdquo;
is also a lot of words to describe  department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve cut my introductions down to a short sentence, that is open to more questions,
and gives me the ability to cater the detail in my responses depending on the questions I&amp;rsquo;m
being asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I study social networks and how things like diseases spread in them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The class was fun and a good mental change from daily graduate school life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessible Education in the United States</title>
      <link>/2017/02/06/accessible-education-in-the-united-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/06/accessible-education-in-the-united-states/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the United States,
higher education aims to be accessible to everyone.
Although historically, college and university degrees were mainly for privileged, white males,
throughout the years,
in order to decrease the socioeconomic gap,
more colleges aimed towards local regions and demographics were created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Historically Black Colleges and Universities,
to Land Grant Schools,
to Community Colleges, each `type&amp;rsquo; of College/University was aimed to be more inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This puts things into perspective and I&amp;rsquo;ve considered teaching at community colleges.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journal: Why am I Journaling?</title>
      <link>/2017/01/30/journal-why-am-i-journaling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/30/journal-why-am-i-journaling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m taking &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lt.vt.edu/grad5104/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Preparing the Future Professoriate&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; this semester at Virginia Tech,
which is one of the core classes for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://graduateschool.vt.edu/transformative-graduate-education-experience/future-professoriate/future-professoriate-certificate.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Future Professoriate Certificate&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The class has us writing &lt;a href=&#34;http://chendaniely.github.io/blog/tags/#pfps17&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; along with weekly journals.
Since I&amp;rsquo;m now transitioning into the phase in my doctoral program where I need to transition into writing papers,
just getting in to the habit of writing more can&amp;rsquo;t hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s work on just writing more,
then focus on tailoring my voice towards different audiences.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
