<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>teaching on Academic</title>
    <link>/tags/teaching/</link>
    <description>Recent content in teaching on Academic</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Changes in Higher Education</title>
      <link>/2017/05/01/changes-in-higher-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/01/changes-in-higher-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a PhD student who already has a Master&amp;rsquo;s degree, it&amp;rsquo;s safe to say that I&amp;rsquo;ve been in school for a long time.
One of the things in higher education that I started to dislike over the years are the ways professors assess students in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a graduate student, more specifically, a PhD student,
a lot of my time should be spent on research.
However, when classes are structured the same way as they were in my undergraduate days,
memorization is the primary form of assessment,
then the point of why I need to take classes as a graduate student seem missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, I feel like almost any form of assessment in a PhD program should be open-everything.
Mainly because, in practice the world of knowledge is always available as a reference manual that can be consulted.
Having to brute memorize reference tables (like statistical distributions),
almost seem like wasted effort.
More important or frequently used bits of information will naturally be remembered as they are used,
but to blindly memorize facts do not assess whether or not a student actually knows the take-away skills
from a class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Class projects and homework assignments seem like a good way to assess students.
At the very least, they have &amp;lsquo;correct&amp;rsquo; answers to a set of problems the course aims to teach,
which becomes a set of reference material for the student in the future.
I have bounded books of old class notes and homeworks that I constantly reference when I am working on statistical analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NYC R Conference</title>
      <link>/2017/04/24/nyc-r-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/24/nyc-r-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just got back from the 3rd annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rstats.nyc/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NYC R Conference&lt;/a&gt; this past weekend.
I have been honored to be one of the few speakers for the 3rd year in a row.
This year&amp;rsquo;s talk, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chendaniely/rstatsnyc_2017-data_scientist&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;So You Want to be a Data Scientist&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
gave a whirlwind tour of the tools and skills needed to be a Data Scientist.
I conveyed all this information in 56 slides and did it in 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day before the conference,
I also ended up &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chendaniely/2017-04-20-nyp_value_institute&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;presenting&lt;/a&gt; my current work on behavior diffusion in social netowrks
and a little of my other work to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nyp.org/valueinstitute/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital’s Value Institute&lt;/a&gt;.
This was probably the more nerve wracking things I&amp;rsquo;ve had to do recently,
presenting my research to a few extremely talented and smart PhDs doing
health analytics for New York Presbyterian Hospital.
But, we had a lot of good meaningful discussion during the talk,
that went overtime and we were kicked out of the room.
That has to be a good sign, right?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing for the Summer</title>
      <link>/2017/04/24/preparing-for-the-summer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/24/preparing-for-the-summer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As the semester comes to an end,
preparing for my lab&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bi.vt.edu/sdal/projects/data-science-for-the-public-good-program&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Data Science for the Public Good Program&lt;/a&gt; begins.
I&amp;rsquo;ve started a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bi-sdal/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub group&lt;/a&gt; to dump the various components we will be using during the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bi.vt.edu/sdal/people/Aaron-Schroeder&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Aaron Schroeder&lt;/a&gt; and I will be the main trainers for the students this summer.
It&amp;rsquo;s our job to teach the students the basic tools needed to be functional in the lab.
We put our initial syllabus in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bi-sdal/workshop&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the semester ends I should have about 2 weeks to finalize all the things to be taught.
Ideally, this workshop repository will be come the basis for a university course in the future.
I know the university library is currently getting numerous people Software-Carpentry Instructors
so they can be more independent in teaching the Software Carpentry materials.
Hopefully by the end of the summer, the DSPG syllabus will be worked out to a point that I can present and show
the newly minted SWC instructors at VT, for them to adapt for their own needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime,
There are a lot of readings and things I need to familiarize myself with before the summer program starts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tidyverse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://r4ds.had.co.nz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R for Data Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/bookdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;bookdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jennybc.github.io/purrr-tutorial/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;purrr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://forcats.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;forcats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tidyverse/tidyr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tidyr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s probably more things I&amp;rsquo;m forgetting to list, but that&amp;rsquo;s more than enough for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention I need to prepare my poster for &lt;a href=&#34;https://epiresearch.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Society for Epidemiologic Research (SER)&lt;/a&gt;,
and pretty much finish up my book that will be the basis for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://scipy2017.scipy.org/ehome/220975/493418/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SciPy 2017 Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working While Pursuing a PhD</title>
      <link>/2017/04/17/working-while-pursuing-a-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/17/working-while-pursuing-a-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My lab has extended me an opportunity to be a research scientist and helping out our current senior data scientist
with the daily analytics and IT support the lab needs.
It&amp;rsquo;s a very enticing opportunity, but I need to stop and think about my options&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d get paid more!
What kind of graduate student would not want that?
But I would really need to consider and clarify with my advisor and rest of my lab how
this can fit in with my PhD.
I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be doing my PhD longer than I have to,
and ideally I would be put on a series of projects that can be used for my final dissertation topic.
However, if I am a staff member of the lab, I will have less freedom of what my topic would be.
Of course, if I spent the after hours working on my dissertation,
I could do whatever I wanted, but that might not be a feasible solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job will give me financial stability,
but currently as a PhD student,
I have a lot of academic freedom that I might loose.
Since most of my work is computational,
it can easily be done remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily my advisor will becoming to down in a few weeks.
We&amp;rsquo;ll discuss this further then.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Education in the United States</title>
      <link>/2017/04/10/education-in-the-united-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/10/education-in-the-united-states/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As people start sharing their educational experiences from around the world,
I realized how lucky I am to have been educated in New York City,
and how much less the United States focuses on education when compared to many other countries around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Access</title>
      <link>/2017/04/10/open-access/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/10/open-access/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Open&amp;rdquo; has played in important role in my life the last few years.
It all began when I was an attendee at a &lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Software-Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org/blog/2016/10/what_swc_means_to_me.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; back in 2013.
Before then, I only knew about Open Access and Open Source,
but wasn&amp;rsquo;t active in any Open community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week is &lt;a href=&#34;https://vtnews.vt.edu/articles/2017/04/univlib-opendataweek.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Open Data Week at Virginia Tech&lt;/a&gt;,
and it begins with
an &amp;ldquo;Open Research/Open Data Forum [on] Transparency, Sharing, and Reproducibility in Scholarship&amp;rdquo;,
which I was honored to be apart of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Access typically refers to providing research publications free from restrictions on access.
In academic publishing,
this is mainly aimed towards paywalls,
where an individual needs to pay to see a published paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate around Open Access is highly debated,
mainly because there is a lot of money in the scholarly publication business.
I&amp;rsquo;ve had the mindset that Open Access or not, it is just a business funding model.
The other components of Open (data, source, education) are better and faster ways of disseminate
information to the masses without a fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am honored to be one of the panelists on today&amp;rsquo;s Open Data Forum:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniel Chen (Ph.D. candidate in Genetics, Bioinformatics, and Computational Biology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Karen DePauw (Vice President and Dean for Graduate Education)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sally Morton (Dean, College of Science)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jon Petters (Data Management Consultant, University Libraries)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Radcliffe (Professor, English, College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laura Sands (Professor of Human Development, Center for Gerontology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Daunting&amp;rsquo; might not be the right word,
but that&amp;rsquo;s quite the line-up of speakers + random graduate student.
Someone at the libraries thought it was a good idea,
and has faith in me, so that&amp;rsquo;s a plus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question presented to the panel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One of the main arguments in favor of open research and open data is that the collective benefits to the research system far outweigh the drawbacks. Such benefits include helping to address the problem of reproducibility and opening up new research pathways. Do you agree with this argument? And what are the principal barriers you see in moving us towards this system?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an interesting question, mainly because it seems like we are preaching to the choir,
but one way to see the other side of the argument is looking at the current system of incentives.
Currently, the way academic incentives are structured for promotion are not conducive for open collaboration and open data.
Mainly because by freely diving out data, one may loose the ability for a paper authorship.
Granted there are counter arguments for this, but fear is a powerful motivator,
and when productivity is measured by number of publications,
potentially losing publications is enough of a detractor for many to not pursuit Openness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tech &amp; Innovation in Higher Ed</title>
      <link>/2017/04/03/tech-innovation-in-higher-ed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/03/tech-innovation-in-higher-ed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How faculty (higher education) are using and/or reacting to social media, MOOCs, and/or other &amp;ldquo;disruptive&amp;rdquo; technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite talks is the one given by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1e26rp6qPbA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Greg Wilson at Scipy 2014&lt;/a&gt; about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000research.com/articles/3-62/v2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;lessons learned&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Software-Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;.
Software-Carpentry aims to teach the &lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1001745&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Best Practices for Scientific Computing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific computing is a skill lacking in education,
especially in higher education where research is being performed.
What is lacking in scientific computing education is the lack of courses for the researcher,
rather than the computer scientist.
I think this is why MOOCs came to existence,
people found the current system of teaching courses too restrictive so they went outside the university and created the course they wanted.
For example, trying to get a &lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org/blog/2016/02/swc-as-a-university-course.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Software-Carpentry workshop as a university course&lt;/a&gt; is difficult because
different departments around the university feel like its their jurisdiction to create the course (I&amp;rsquo;m looking at you computer science).
However, faculty are already heavily burdened with trying to fund themselves with grants and performing other responsibilities
as faculty, that it&amp;rsquo;s hard to create a generic multi-disciplinary course on scientific research.
Also, assessing students is tricky in the software-carpentry context because of how many hours a class can meet per week.
SWC works because it&amp;rsquo;s a very condensed 2 day workshop aimed to teach all the basics in Bash, Git, Python or R, and SQL.
To formulate and re-arrange the workshop into a weekly course means many skills will not be integrated until the very end.
In which case you risk loosing students.
MOOCs are just a natural evolution to address the limitations in a university setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MOOCs have their own problems, mainly attrition.
Only a small fraction of the students who begin a MOOC complete it.
I am guilty of starting courses and not finishing the course, or only hand-picking a few topics relevant to myself.
But, I am happy to know the content is there for when I need to go back to it one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think many of the backlash towards MOOCs are the same criticisms regarding open eduction and open textbooks:
how can something &amp;lsquo;free&amp;rsquo; be good?
My response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many teachers begin teaching Calculus I every September when the new school year begins?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many of those teachers are writing his/her own curriculum?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many of those teachers lean the same mistakes on their first year to fix on the next iteration?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many hours of resources were wasted for all the teachers to learn the same mistake?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What if all that knowledge was already compiled into an open curriculum to be refined?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are companies that teach MOOCs.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datacamp.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DataCamp&lt;/a&gt; is an example.
They have a subscription service where experts in a field aim to teach a programming concept.
This allows companies to purchase bulk subscriptions for their employees to give them targeted training without having to come up with their own in-house resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe if we have people pay a dollar for a MOOC, they will feel obligated to finish the course?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The People that Keep Me Sane</title>
      <link>/2017/04/03/the-people-that-keep-me-sane/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/03/the-people-that-keep-me-sane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Coming from CUNY Hunter College, I never really had the typical &amp;lsquo;college experience&amp;rsquo;.
Going to college for me was almost no different than going to high school since so many people
were commuters; there was no campus, especially when compared to Virginia Tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I snowboard.
After not going during the 2 years of my master&amp;rsquo;s,
I decided the first thing I did when I started Tech was to find the ski/snowboarding club
and go on a big winter trip.
So I joined VT Snow my first year at VT,
and I got go fly out to Colorado for the first time ever to go Snowboarding.
I was the only graduate student who was in the club, and it was great.
I met a bunch of new friends who all knew how to snowboard and have fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also SCUBA dive.
My second year, I ended up getting involved with the SCUBA club (SCVT) because my family had a winter break trip
planned out to Australia.
I ended up getting my SDI Advanced Adventure Diver last semester to prepare for the trip to see the Great Barrier Reefs.
This semester I&amp;rsquo;m planning to finish my Rescue Diver,
and hope to start a Dive Master course over the summer.
Maybe by the time I finish my PhD I&amp;rsquo;ll also be a SCUBA instructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to have friends outside of your discipline, especially in a PhD program.
As isolating as life can be,
you definitely do not want to be constantly reminded about the work you know you should be doing when you&amp;rsquo;re
giving yourself a well needed mental break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that these sports require so much mental focus, allows me to just forget about everything else.
Plus the views on top of a mountain really makes you feel like you&amp;rsquo;re on top of the world,
and the calm weightless feeling while diving is meditative.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientific Programming</title>
      <link>/2017/03/27/scientific-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/27/scientific-programming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Software-Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; played an &lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org/blog/2016/10/what_swc_means_to_me.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;integral part&lt;/a&gt; of who I am today.
I am always trying to learn and follow best practices in the context of scientific programming,
which I think is a neglected area in research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental problem is the incentive structure in academia,
where productivity is measured by the number of papers published.
The downside of tis pressure is that quality of analytics and code will suffer
to get the results for the paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of us who are doing research and realized how much coding is needed for analytics
see programming as a means to get results.
Teaching yourself a technical skill is extremely difficult without mentorship.
It&amp;rsquo;s very easy to learn and pick up bad habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve seen and heard multiple times that the code is written in a particular way solely because it &amp;lsquo;works&amp;rsquo;,
without considering that it can potentially have bugs in it and might need to be patched.
It&amp;rsquo;s extremely frustrating when I try to provide guidance and try to teach a skill,
but am confronted with &amp;ldquo;No. I don&amp;rsquo;t have time for that&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It only makes me wonder how much this happens in scholarly research,
and can also explain why science has a reproducibility problem.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should You Attend Grad School?</title>
      <link>/2017/03/27/should-you-attend-grad-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/27/should-you-attend-grad-school/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been asked a few times about whether one should attend graduate school.
I usually follow up by asking whether they are planning to do a Master&amp;rsquo;s or a Doctorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it&amp;rsquo;s a master&amp;rsquo;s, sure, why not.
Master&amp;rsquo;s programs are typically no longer than 2 years and very well structured.
You come in with a cohort of students, and everyone struggles together and becomes friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PhD programs are much more variable and different.
First, the cohort of students are much smaller.
Second, unless there is Master&amp;rsquo;s along the way,
PhD programs will be unique to each student.
Meaning you&amp;rsquo;ll struggle on your own.
It&amp;rsquo;s important to consider your current support network when thinking about PhD programs.
I cannot stress this enough.
It&amp;rsquo;s a stressful, lonely, and isolating world out there,
and you really need to make sure you have a solid support network to help you though the ups and downs.
There is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://qz.com/547641/theres-an-awful-cost-to-getting-a-phd-that-no-one-talks-about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;awful cost&lt;/a&gt; to getting a PhD,
and there&amp;rsquo;s a reason why &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/careers/2017/04/phd-students-face-significant-mental-health-challenges&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mental health&lt;/a&gt; disorders are common among PhD students&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From NYC to Blacksburg, VA</title>
      <link>/2017/03/20/from-nyc-to-blacksburg-va/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/20/from-nyc-to-blacksburg-va/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m from New York City.
Born and raised in Queens, and went to school in Manhattan for high school, college, and masters.
So, coming down to rural Blacksburg, VA has been a big change in scenery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blacksburg is a beautiful town.
There are many aspects of the area that I love: clean air, quiet, and plenty of outdoor activities.
As someone pursuing a PhD, I am essentially a professional student,
so the lack of distractions is much appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do love the fact that many outdoor activities are so easily accessible in the area.
Hiking trails are as close as a 15 minute drive away,
The New River and Blacksburg Quarry for SCUBA diving are within 15 minutes away as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest things I miss about NYC is the food and pizza.
There is so much good ethnic cuisine that Blacksburg does not have.
The way around it is to try and cook it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had subscribed to Blue Apron last semester,
and it really kickstarted cooking meals at home versus buying and ordering food.
The 30-60 minutes to cook and eat is a nice distraction from the daily stress from school.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Story</title>
      <link>/2017/03/20/my-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/20/my-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How did I get to where I am today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Early&lt;/h2&gt;
I&#39;ve always been surrounded by computers.
My parents both studied Computer Science,
and my dad holds a Master&#39;s in Computer Science and works as a software developer.
Growing up, all my computers were company hand-me-downs,
but it allowed me to be lucky enough to always have a computer in the house.
I liked to tinker, not as a programmer, or hacker, but more of a user.
As a child, one of the first things I&#39;d do when I open a program would to find the preferences tab of a program,
and learn what settings were available, and learn how to use a piece of software.

I competed in the ThinkQuest Internet Challenge in the 5th grade,
and co-authored an award winning website on Epilepsy.

&lt;h2&gt;High School&lt;/h2&gt;
I was fortunate to attend Stuyvesant High School, a specialized math and science high school in NYC.
One semester of programming was a mandatory for all sophomores.
Looking back, I&#39;m amazed the amount of material covered in a semester of school:
Netlogo (where I co-wrote a BlackJack game),
Scheme (where I wrote a visual calculator that worked with negative values, e.g., xx - xxx = -x),
and Python (where I wrote a strategy for Prisoner&#39;s Dilemma).

&lt;h2&gt;College&lt;/h2&gt;
My undergraduate years was focused on getting into medical school.
I ended up graduating with a major in Psychology with a concentration in Behavioral Neuroscience,
and minors in Biology and Computer Science.

My high school experience in computer science was a bit traumatic,
and prevented me from programming courses until my final couple of years in college.
Bioinformatics was a major I was highly interested in,
but the math and computer science requirements scared me into Psychology.

I ended up in Behavioral Neuroscience because it was a small and new program mainly aimed towards the Honors Students.
Still focused on getting into medical school,
this was the best choice at the time since it gave me wet-lab experience and the
chance to work closely with professors for letters of recommendation.

During all of this I worked with Dr. Samuel Sigal in Hepatology at Wiel Cornell and NYU.
I was on the clinical trials coordination team and got to interact with patients
undergoing various Phase III clinical trials to cure Hepatitis C.

&lt;h2&gt;Masters&lt;/h2&gt;
I got my Master&#39;s in Public Health because of the clinical research skills it would give me.
It allowed me to build on the basic statistics knowledge I had from college,
and learn the epidemiology and biostatistics skills for clinical and observational study design and regression analysis.
I was lucky to be in the Department of Epidemiology when Sandro Galea was Chair of the department.
Under his guide, the department had a big push to study complex systems approaches to public health.
Here I got to work with Kerry Keyes, Magna Certa, and Melissa Tracy in a R01 studying injury from alcohol consumption in NYC.
I also met Mark Orr, who became my Master&#39;s Thesis Advisor on measuring and simulating how behaviors spread in social networks.

I learned to love teaching when I was a Quantitative Methods (Epidemiology I and Biostat I)
Teaching Assistant for Dana March.
This let me to join Software Carpentry when I after a workshop led by Justin Ely and David Wade Farley.

I attended a Software Carpentry workshop when I took Introduction to Data Science during my Masters.
The course was taught by Rachael Shutt, Kayur Patel, and Jared Lander.
I learned R, and it changed my life.
What started out as a Master&#39;s in Public Health to gain clinical research skills before going to medical school
quickly evolved into Data Science where data analytics applied to health became my new interest.

&lt;h2&gt;Now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently at Virginia Tech in the Genetics, Bioinformatics, and Computational Biology program.
My lab, the Social and Decision Analytics Laboratory, is in Arlington, VA,
and I occasionally have small consulting and side projects to help pay the bills and put
guacamole on my Chipotle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What You Call Yourself is Important</title>
      <link>/2017/03/13/what-you-call-yourself-is-important/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/13/what-you-call-yourself-is-important/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a PhD &lt;em&gt;Student&lt;/em&gt;, not a candidate&amp;hellip; yet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Ethics</title>
      <link>/2017/03/12/research-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/12/research-ethics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://ori.hhs.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Office of Research Integrity&lt;/a&gt; (ORI) oversees and directs Public Health Service (PHS) research integrity activities on behalf of the Secretary of Health and Human Services with the exception of the regulatory research integrity activities of the Food and Drug Administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a location on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ori.hhs.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ORI website&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ori.hhs.gov/case_summary&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Misconduct Case Summaries&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/em&gt;.
There are currently 7 cases for 2016:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case Summary: Cullinane, Andrew R.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case Summary: D&amp;rsquo;Souza, Karen M.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case Summary: Forbes, Meredyth M.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case Summary: Li, Zhiyu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case Summary: Malhotra, Ricky&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case Summary: Pastorino, John G.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case Summary: Walker, Kenneth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the cases involved &amp;ldquo;ORI [finding that the] Respondent engaged in research misconduct by falsifying and/or fabricating data&amp;rdquo;.
This is a symptom of the problems in academic publications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only &amp;ldquo;Significant&amp;rdquo; results get published.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provoking results get published in &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; journals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Academic productivity is measured in number of publications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It creates a feedback loop with perverse intensives.
In the worst case scenario,
self-governance in the form of peer review is also inadequate.
The story of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoshitaka_Fujii&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yoshitaka Fujii&lt;/a&gt;, comes to mind in this scenario.
It&amp;rsquo;s easy for me to criticize the system,
and I can&amp;rsquo;t say I have a particularly good solution, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting about the cases is the fact that most of them are related to medicine.
This can profound consequences on how the public will perceive new medical treatments.
As far as consequences go, all the cases ended up in a 3 year probation for the offending member,
and can no longer serve as an advisor.
Additionally, all papers related needed to be retracted or corrected.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Learning Works</title>
      <link>/2017/03/06/how-learning-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/06/how-learning-works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Susan Ambrose&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/How-Learning-Works-Research-Based-Principles/dp/0470484101&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How Learning Works&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; is probably one of the best investments for people who teach.
The next best (time) investment is reading Greg Wilson&amp;rsquo;s paper on &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000research.com/articles/3-62/v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Software Carpentry: lessons learned&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve watched Greg Wilson&amp;rsquo;s corresponding &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FtKO619O5g0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PyCon 2014&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1e26rp6qPbA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SciPy 2014&lt;/a&gt; talk numerous times,
and is well worth the listen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Modest Advice for Graduate Students</title>
      <link>/2017/03/06/some-modest-advice-for-graduate-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/06/some-modest-advice-for-graduate-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://stearnslab.yale.edu/some-modest-advice-graduate-students&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Some Modest Advice for Graduate Students&lt;/a&gt;
by Stephen C. Stearns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;tl;dr:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always Prepare for the Worst&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody cares about you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You Must Know Why Your Work is Important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Psychological Problems are the Biggest Barrier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid Taking Lectures - They’re Usually Inefficient&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a Proposal and Get It Criticized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage Your Advisors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Types of Theses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start Publishing Early&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t Look Down on a Master’s Thesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish Regularly, But Not Too Much&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a writeup that&amp;rsquo;s always worth a read every now and then.
It helps put things into perspective and gets you thinking about how your graduate career is advancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve learned in my undergraduate years how to navigate the academic system and carve out my own path.
It&amp;rsquo;s served me well and gives my advisors confidence that I know what I am doing.
I&amp;rsquo;m also lucky to work with people that gives me a lot of academic freedom to explore and work on problems that are interesting to me,
but also gives me advice and point me in the right away when I wonder too far off course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I am finishing up my coursework,
I personally know I need to address my (lack of) writing.
The first step of solving a problem is acknowledging the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to write more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching and Mentoring</title>
      <link>/2017/02/27/teaching-and-mentoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/27/teaching-and-mentoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Software-Carpentry&lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; has made be a better teacher because of the way we collect feedback during our workshops.
When teaching a technical class,
we use low-tech sticky notes to signify whether individuals need help or not:
Green for no help needed, Red for help needed.
This is extremely effective while teaching.
As an instructor all you need to look for is a red sticky note and you know someone has a question,
or if everyone has a green sticky note, the class is following along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The python community is proactive in mentoring.
During the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pydata.org/carolinas2016/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PyData Carolinas 2016&lt;/a&gt; conference,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WillingCarol&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Carol Willing&lt;/a&gt; talked about how small nudges and discussions can be enough to mentor someone.
I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to be a mentor to my students I teach though my lab&amp;rsquo;s summer program.
There is a misconception that mentoring is a &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; job.
It&amp;rsquo;s not.
The right piece of advice at the right time,
can change an individual&amp;rsquo;s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think about the most influential people in my life,
and it&amp;rsquo;s mainly a series of seemingly random encounters and discussions
that helped shaped the person I am today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where Do I Fit in Academia?</title>
      <link>/2017/02/20/where-do-i-fit-in-academia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/20/where-do-i-fit-in-academia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s always a good idea to take a break and think about all that&amp;rsquo;s going on in life in perspective.
As I approach the end of the coursework phase of my PhD program,
I need to think about what&amp;rsquo;s next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My preliminary exam&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but beyond that,
I need to think about the (glorious) life after I graduate.
Do I go to industry? or stay in Academia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, my duties are closer aligned to that of a scientific research software engineer.
I enjoy building scientific software and tools,
and enjoy doing data analysis.
What I dread is writing.
Mainly because I am slow and terrible at it.
While this is a feedback loop that I need to break,
my disdain for writing means that I am not academically &amp;ldquo;productive&amp;rdquo;.
No grants, no papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past year at Virginia Tech and taking the Future Professoriate Class,
working in the library seems like a good academic fit for my academic toolkit,
or my love for teaching has directed me into looking into Professor of Practice positions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Communicating Science</title>
      <link>/2017/02/13/communicating-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/13/communicating-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The communication science workshop at class reminds me of the various acting warm-up exercise I did when I took an acting class in high school.
The drills require individuals to coordinate and communicate with other people in the room,
but also serves as an icebreaker by doing &amp;lsquo;silly&amp;rsquo; things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first exercise we did in class was to describe our current research.
This is a skill that I have refined over the past few years as a PhD student.
I remember when I first started my PhD program,
I would try to describe my department, program, and current work &amp;lsquo;correctly&amp;rsquo;,
only to see a blank stare from the person I would be talking to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Genetics, Bioinformatics, and Computational Biology&amp;rdquo; is a lot of big words.
Furthermore, &amp;ldquo;Interdisciplinary between Mathematics, Statistics, Life Science, and Computer Science&amp;rdquo;
is also a lot of words to describe  department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve cut my introductions down to a short sentence, that is open to more questions,
and gives me the ability to cater the detail in my responses depending on the questions I&amp;rsquo;m
being asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I study social networks and how things like diseases spread in them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The class was fun and a good mental change from daily graduate school life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessible Education in the United States</title>
      <link>/2017/02/06/accessible-education-in-the-united-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/06/accessible-education-in-the-united-states/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the United States,
higher education aims to be accessible to everyone.
Although historically, college and university degrees were mainly for privileged, white males,
throughout the years,
in order to decrease the socioeconomic gap,
more colleges aimed towards local regions and demographics were created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Historically Black Colleges and Universities,
to Land Grant Schools,
to Community Colleges, each `type&amp;rsquo; of College/University was aimed to be more inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This puts things into perspective and I&amp;rsquo;ve considered teaching at community colleges.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impostor Syndrome: Am I Qualified?</title>
      <link>/2017/02/06/impostor-syndrome-am-i-qualified/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/06/impostor-syndrome-am-i-qualified/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impostor syndrome (also known as impostor phenomenon or fraud syndrome) is a concept describing high-achieving individuals who are marked by an inability to internalize their accomplishments and a persistent fear of being exposed as a &amp;ldquo;fraud&amp;rdquo;.
- &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really shouldn&amp;rsquo;t feel impostor syndrome.
There are many things I can list that point to my accomplishments,
yet, I still fall victim to impostor syndrome.
It&amp;rsquo;s a phenomenon that is constantly talked about and written about.
There was an article in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/10/26/your-money/learning-to-deal-with-the-impostor-syndrome.html?_r=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt; back in 2015,
and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/imposters/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://cestlaz.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mike Zamansky&lt;/a&gt;,
a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stuyspec.com/news/computer-science-coordinator-michael-zamansky-resigns&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;former computer science teacher&lt;/a&gt; at my &lt;a href=&#34;http://stuy.enschool.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;high school&lt;/a&gt;,
and Distinguished Lecturer at my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hunter.cuny.edu/main/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;alma mater&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;High-achieving individuals&amp;rdquo; strive to better themselves by surrounding themselves with people who are better than they are.
We all have our idols and heroes.
By following them, and listening to their mistakes and journeys,
we slowly improve ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I was listening to the [Partially Derivative Podcast].
At the end of their &lt;a href=&#34;http://partiallyderivative.com/podcast/2016/06/09/s2e12-decartes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;June 09, 2016 episode (S2E12), &amp;ldquo;Descartes Before the Horse&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://chrisalbon.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Chris Albon&lt;/a&gt; talks about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friendship_paradox&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;friendship paradox&lt;/a&gt;.
The general gist of it goes something along the lines of:
people tend to observe and be in contact with people with more friends than they do.
This idea can be extrapolated to essentially say,
we observe people doing things that are better than ourselves.
This perpetuates imposer syndrome and can explain why we always feel inferior to other people;
we see people doing things that they are good at and we are not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journal: Why am I Journaling?</title>
      <link>/2017/01/30/journal-why-am-i-journaling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/30/journal-why-am-i-journaling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m taking &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lt.vt.edu/grad5104/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Preparing the Future Professoriate&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; this semester at Virginia Tech,
which is one of the core classes for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://graduateschool.vt.edu/transformative-graduate-education-experience/future-professoriate/future-professoriate-certificate.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Future Professoriate Certificate&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The class has us writing &lt;a href=&#34;http://chendaniely.github.io/blog/tags/#pfps17&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; along with weekly journals.
Since I&amp;rsquo;m now transitioning into the phase in my doctoral program where I need to transition into writing papers,
just getting in to the habit of writing more can&amp;rsquo;t hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s work on just writing more,
then focus on tailoring my voice towards different audiences.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mission Statements</title>
      <link>/2017/01/30/mission-statements/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/30/mission-statements/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Mission statements and reflections on higher education institutions (plus one high school) that I&amp;rsquo;ve attended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;reflection&#34;&gt;Reflection&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not surprising that the institutions that have a more specific academic focus, will have a more specific mission statement.
The Mailman school of public health&amp;rsquo;s mission is devoted in improving public health, and
Stuyvesant High school, is focused on science, mathematics, and technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the other Colleges and Universities, the missions are much more general,
and the ones located in New York City, mention the city, whereas Virginia Tech mentions the entire Commonwealth of Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some background information about the Macaulay Honors College,
it is a college, but the students who attend it have a &amp;lsquo;home&amp;rsquo; college in one of the various colleges in the City University of New York (CUNY) system.
I attended in the Macaulay Honors College at Hunter College of the City University of New York.
The fact that all the other mission statements are multiple sentences long,
makes me wonder if Macaulay&amp;rsquo;s statement is meant to extend which ever home college the student goes to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the colleges and universities reference research,
it would be interesting to hear from the other members in the class who may not have attended research institutions and how those
mission statements differ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;mission-statements&#34;&gt;Mission statements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;virginia-tech&#34;&gt;Virginia Tech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ut Prosim&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;em&gt;That I May Serve&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (Virginia Tech) is a public land-grant university serving the Commonwealth of Virginia, the nation, and the world community. The discovery and dissemination of new knowledge are central to its mission. Through its focus on teaching and learning, research and discovery, and outreach and engagement, the university creates, conveys, and applies knowledge to expand personal growth and opportunity, advance social and community development, foster economic competitiveness, and improve the quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mailman-school-of-public-health&#34;&gt;Mailman School of Public Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To address the most important issues that challenge the health of populations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To identify effective approaches to the prevention of disease and disability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create health equity in a diverse world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To educate the next generation of public health leaders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We aim to achieve our mission locally and globally through innovative science, education, and leadership.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are guided by the fundamental principle that health is a human right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;columbia-university&#34;&gt;Columbia University&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In lumine Tuo videbimus lumen&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;em&gt;In Thy light shall we see light&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia University is one of the world&amp;rsquo;s most important centers of research and at the same time a distinctive and distinguished learning environment for undergraduates and graduate students in many scholarly and professional fields. The University recognizes the importance of its location in New York City and seeks to link its research and teaching to the vast resources of a great metropolis. It seeks to attract a diverse and international faculty and student body, to support research and teaching on global issues, and to create academic relationships with many countries and regions. It expects all areas of the university to advance knowledge and learning at the highest level and to convey the products of its efforts to the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;macaulay-honors-college&#34;&gt;Macaulay Honors College&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Macaulay Honors College offers exceptional students transformative opportunities to develop their potential beyond what they ever imagined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cuny-hunter-college&#34;&gt;CUNY Hunter College&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mihi cura futuri&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;em&gt;The care of the future is mine&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hunter College of the City University of New York, a distinguished public university,
values learning in the liberal arts and sciences as a cornerstone of individual development
and a vital foundation for a more just and inclusive society. Continuing our long tradition
of expanding opportunity, we seek students from all backgrounds to engage in a rigorous
educational experience that prepares them to become leaders and innovators in their
communities and in the world.  Hunter also contributes to intellectual discourse by
supporting excellent scholarship and creative activity by its accomplished faculty.&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunter undergraduate, graduate, and professional curricula challenge students to think
critically - to approach problems from multiple perspectives, distinguish the questions
each raises, and recognize the kinds of evidence each values. The College&amp;rsquo;s academic
programs stress the significance of human diversity, emphasize research and artistic
creation, and invite students to extend their education beyond campus. We cultivate the
qualities our graduates need to thrive in their chosen careers and make a difference as
active citizens.&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We embrace our setting at the heart of New York City - we seek to draw on its energy,
capitalize on its remarkable resources, weave it into the fabric of our teaching, research,
and creative expression, and give back to it through our service and citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;stuyvesant-high-school&#34;&gt;Stuyvesant High School&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pro Scientia Atque Sapientia&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;em&gt;For knowledge and wisdom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stuyvesant High School has been a symbol of excellence in education for over a century. Our mission is to continue and enhance that commitment by providing an environment which will nurture and enhance the special academic talents of the students admitted to Stuyvesant. The educational heritage of Stuyvesant is deeply rooted in the tradition of Science, Mathematics and Technology. This has been the foundation of our educational success and must remain the cornerstone of our educational program. Within this context, the goal of this institution is to instill the intellectual, moral and humanistic values necessary for each child to achieve his/her maximum potential as a student and as a caring citizen of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
